Thank you for joining this session
where we are going to talk about-
-how we are building an open source
government application platform-
-in the cloud.
We are three members of the team that's
building the Altinn 3 platform-
-for Norwegian Digitalization Agency.
The team consists of members
from the agency itself-
-and consultants
from different companies.
My name is Rune T. Larsen,
and I work for Accenture Technology.
I've been doing that since 2005.
I've been working on
the Altinn platform since 2008,-
-and I was part of the team that
built the 2. generation of Altinn.
I'm a developer
and technical architect,-
-and I do most of my coding in .NET.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Nina Kylstad.
I also work at Accenture Technology,-
-and I've been working there
for the past six years.
For the past five years, I've also
been working on the Altinn platform.
I am a developer
and technical architect.
I like to think of myself
as a full-stack developer.
But I do work
mostly front-end these days.
Outside of work,
I have a one-year-old-
-who keeps me busy most of the time.
When I do have some spare time,
I like to read,-
-and I've also
dusted off my sewing machine-
-in these times when
we're staying so much at home.
Hi, guys!
My name is Stephanie Buadu.
I've been with Avanade
and the Altinn team since 2018.
On this project, I've focused mostly
on the back-end part of our solution-
-and also our integrations
with Altinn 2.
In my spare time,
I quite like knitting.
That's a great hobby
to combine with Netflix,-
-so I do quite a bit of that as well.
In this presentation, we're going to
talk about what Altinn is.
Give a little introduction
for you guys who doesn't know that.
We're going to
talk about the Altinn 3 project.
How that started
and the technical principles
we are using when building the new platform.
And we'll go into details
about the new platform,-
-the components
and the solution we are creating.
Then we are going through
the cloud architecture-
-and the components we are using
as part of the solution.
We are going to give you
the current status-
-and what we will be working on next.
At the end, we open up for questions,
so please ask questions.
So, what is Altinn?
Imagine you work
for a government agency-
-that needs to get data
from the citizens of Norway.
Maybe you want them
to report their covid-19 symptoms.
Maybe you want
a digital service online-
-where they can receive that data.
Then Altinn is the platform for you.
Altinn is an Internet portal
for dialogue between the citizens,-
-the businesses
and the agencies of Norway.
It's also a technical platform-
-where the agencies can build
and host their digital services.
Altinn was one of the first platforms
as a service provider,-
-because it already started
back in 2002.
When three agencies joined forces-
-to build a common platform
for reporting to the government.
And in 2003,
the first generation was launched.
In 2010,
the second generation went live.
And during those years, more than
50 agencies had joined the platform.
Including the armed forces,
the police, health-
-and many more covering most
of the government sectors of Norway.
There are now
more than 1,000 digital services-
-available through the platform.
That includes everything
from naming your firstborn-
-to report an aircraft incident.
Almost all businesses in Norway
uses Altinn every year.
And as this diagram shows,-
-almost everyone from 13 to 110
uses Altinn every year.
In Altinn,
everyone has their own inbox-
-where they find their communication
with the government.
You also have a service catalogue-
-where you can find your
digital service and what you need.
Having this common platform
is quite unique.
It's regarded as one of the reasons-
-that Norway is a leader
in digital government.
Another good functionaliy is that-
-every functionality
is available through APIs.
A lot of software vendors have
implemented integration with Altinn.
You can submit your tax report
directly from your financial system.
Gartner regards Altinn
as one of the top five-
-government technical platforms
in the world.
So back again to the agency-
-and the need for having data
from the citizens.
From what I said, maybe you think
Altinn 2 is the perfect platform.
But there are some limitations.
We based the current platform
on physical hardware.
So even if our traffic
varies from 100,000 a day-
-to 2,5 million a day,-
-we are scaled the same
all year long.
As an agency today, you will
need to make a digital service-
-that is well supported
on mobile and on desktop.
But we are using Infopath, and it's
limited what you can do with that.
There's a limitation
to what kind of process flow-
-you can support for the end-users.
It's quite time consuming
to do testing-
-because every time
we do a little change,-
-we need to deploy it
through the test environment.
And version control
is done through SharePoint,-
-so it's very difficult to understand
what kind of changes-
-you or others had done
previous on your digital service.
And when you're done testing
and ready to go into production,-
-on today's platform, you need to get
help from a technician to deploy it.
Those are some of the limitations-
-we have started building
on the next generation of Altinn.
So, this project
started already back in 2016.
And we had at that time
looked into what kind of product-
-could replace Infopath.
But we realized that maybe we
should build something from scratch.
So we did a small proof of concept
at that time.
Are we able to build a platform
using ASP.NET Core?
And we kind of: Yes, it's possible.
And in 2018 we were ready to do
a full-fledged proof of concept.
We wanted to build a new platform
using .NET Core.
We wanted to use React as front-end,
and Docker and Kubernetes.
And in the spring of 2018,-
-we started to verify:
Are we able to do this?
And during the summer of 2018
we were saying:
We were able to prove
our main concept.
We are going to build
a UI-designer using React.
We then finalized the concept,-
-and got ready to start
a minimum viable product project.
And that is what we are
presenting to you today.
So what is our concept
of the new platform?
We will let the developers
working for the agencies-
-be able to develop,
by themselves or as a group,-
-digital services, deploy it
to production as containers-
-to a public cloud infrastructure.
And all that without you
needing to know programming-
-or anything about
cloud infrastructure.
Pretty cool.
So, to do this new platform,-
-we defined
some architecture principles.
I'm just going to mention
the five most important ones.
We want to be open source.
We want others to use our platform
and components if they want.
Other agencies
want to use it internally-
-or maybe a different country.
And we also want contribution
from the agency-
-that needs some features
to their platform.
So all our code
is available on GitHub.
All our issues
are available on GitHub.
And we only use tools and framework
that are open source.
The second principle
is that we really want-
-the platform to be loved.
So we build with tools
that the developers like.
So we have chosen
the most loved web framework,-
-according to Stack Overflow, React.
We are using the most loved back-end
framework, that is .NET Core.
And we are using
the most loved platform-
-since we are using Linux containers
based on Docker.
And everything is
built around Visual Studio Code,-
-that is the most loved
development environment.
We truly love
working with our platform,-
-and we believe that others will too.
These are some of the tools
we have been using in our platform.
The third principle is that we are
building everything as microservices.
We want to scale independently
the different components.
We want to be able to deploy them.
To have teams responsible
for different components.
Every component
is deployed as a microservice,-
-and all the digital services
are created and deployed-
-as a microservice.
The fourth principle
is also very important for us.
Because we are going to end up with
a big infrastructure in the cloud.
And we are not able
to run that by ourselves-
-if we're going to
manage it as a team.
So we favor using managed services
available in Azure.
As an example
Azure Kubernetes Service.
Stephanie will tell you
more about that later.
And the last one.
Application owners
will be isolated from each other.
We don't want an application owner-
-to be able to affect the service
for others-
-or be able to
access data for others.
So we have isolated infrastructure
for every application owner.
And we also have isolated
and separated data storage-
-for every application owner.
Nina is going to tell you more about
the solution we are building.
Thank you, Rune.
So we had our overall concept,-
-and we had
our architecture principles-
the proof of concept ready.
And based on this,
we started building our solutions.
Altinn 3 is made up of
three solutions that work together.
First we have
the Altinn Studio Solution.
This is our design-time solution-
-to create, develop
and deploy applications,-
-or apps as we call them.
We have the Altinn Apps Solution.
This is the collection
of all of the running apps-
-and the Kubernetes clusters
on which they run.
Finally we have
the Altinn Platform Solution,-
-which provides the common
back-end functionality for the apps.
Let's look at how
these three solutions work together-
-to support the next generation-
-of digital services
for the people of Norway.
So let's go back to this scenario
of a government agency-
-that wants to collect some data,-
-and they want to create
a digital service to do this.
And we'll see how we can solve this-
-by creating an app
using the Altinn 3 solutions.
These are some of the key features
that we want to support.
These are also some pain points
from the existing platform-
-that we would like to improve on.
So what is an app in this context?
An app is a digital service-
-in the form of
a stand-alone application.
And this application
exposes some APIs,-
-it has some sort of
graphical user interface-
-and it runs in a Docker container.
So to support this,
we have created an app template.
This is the starting point
for all of the apps.
The app template is
a .NET Core MVC Application,-
-completely standard.
And then we have extended it
with some supporting libraries.
These are projects
that we publish as Nuget packages.
Nuget is .NET's package manager.
And these supporting libraries
contain-
-things like the standard APIs
that the apps should expose,-
-as well as integration
with the Altinn platform.
We've also added
placeholders for custom logic-
-and a set of configuration files-
-that the app developers
can use to configure the apps.
The app also refers to a front-end.
This is a React application-
-that is loaded from a content
delivery network at runtime.
All of the apps use
the same front-end by default.
And the front-end
can then be configured-
-to work with the specific apps.
The front-end integrates
with the app itself-
-via the APIs that the app exposes.
Let's look at how an app developer
can actually customize the app.
As I mentioned,
one of the ways to do this,-
-is through
a set of configuration files.
One of the most important
configurations that we set up,-
-is the process.
The process defines the set of tasks-
-that the end-user that actually
uses the app, must go through.
For example,
think back at our scenario-
-of a government agency
that wants to collect data.
So the end-user
might have to fill in a form.
This would be a Data type task.
They might then have to confirm
that their data is correct.
So this would be a Confirmation task.
Finally they might need to
wait for some response-
-from the agency
they are submitting their data to.
This would be the Feedback type task.
These are the three task types
that we support.
And they can be combined in any way
to create a process.
Defining the process is done through
the process configuration file.
When we set up
our configuration files,-
-we tried where possible to use
existing standards for the format.
For the process,
we used the BPMN 2.0 standard.
This is an XML notation
for defining processes.
We've also used the XACML standard
for our authorization policies.
This is an XML standard
for defining access control.
Now authorization policies
can be applied-
-to the entire app as a whole,
or to specific process tasks.
That was a little bit
about setting up the app-
-using the configuration files.
The app developers can also
customize the apps through code.
As I mentioned, we set up
some placeholders for custom logic.
This is for things like validation,
calculation or pre-filling of data.
But this is
really just the beginning.
App developers
can really do anything they want-
-as long as they
can put it into code.
For example, they could
fetch data from the Altinn platform-
-or from external sources.
They could create and expose APIs.
The list goes on and on.
As I said, if it can be coded,
it can be done.
Now let's take this one step further.
I said that the apps all use
the same front-end by default.
And then that front-end
can be configured.
Imagine that this doesn't cut it.
You can't configure the standard
front-end to do what you want.
Allright - replace it with something
different.
Since we just refer to
the app front-end from the app,-
-you can just refer to something else
and load it at runtime.
Or drop the front-end entirely-
-and have your end-users
go directly to the app via the APIs.
And if we go even further now.
Nothing is really stopping you
from doing the same thing-
-with the app template itself.
If it doesn't work for you, you could
replace it with something different.
Maybe even a Java application...
Personally,
I would not choose to replace-
-our beautiful, amazing .NET app template
with a Java application.
But joking aside,-
-if the standard template
doesn't do it for you,-
-then of course it's possible
to replace it with something else.
We see that in the future
we might actually have-
-a set of app templates
using different technologies-
-that you can choose from
when you are creating an app.
Let's go back now
and assume that you want to keep-
-the app template
and front-end as is-
-and then just work
on configuring it.
As we've said before,
we want the UIs to be modern.
We want them to work
on both desktop and mobile.
One of the ways to configure the UI,-
-is by creating a form
for collecting data.
So we decided to build our own tool-
-instead of using
existing tools to do this.
So we built a drag-and-drop
Forms Editor using React.
And this Forms Editor has
a library of available components,-
-that can be dragged into
the form layout and then configured.
Currently we only support
very simple forms,-
-with a single column layout,
and we do aim to expand on this.
When an app developer works
on configuring a form like this,-
-the actual form configuration
and the definition of the form-
-is stored in a JSON layout file.
This is our form layout file, and
it defines how the form should look.
At runtime, the app front-end
then parses this layout file-
-and renders the form.
This configuration
is for the Data type tasks,-
-so forms are for collecting data.
But we do have the possibility
to configure views-
-for the other task types as well.
That would be Confirmation and
Feedback. We have views for these.
The app owners can then configure
the content that will be shown.
So far I've talked about the apps.
But how do we actually develop apps
into complete digital services?
This is done in
the Altinn Studio Solution.
Altinn Studio
is made up of three parts.
We have the Designer Application.
This is the graphical user interface
-that app developers use
to create and develop their apps.
This is what it looks like.
In the Designer Application, we have
the Forms Builder that I showed you.
We have an editor for setting up
texts for language support.
We have some support
for simple code editing,-
-using an embedded code editor,
and of course deploy.
The Designer Application integrates
with the Repository Application.
This is where all the apps
in Altinn Studio are stored.
The Repository Application
is built on Gitea.
This is an open source
code hosting solution that uses GIT.
And it looks like this,
a little bit like GitHub.
Each app in Altinn Studio
is stored in a GIT Repository.
When an app developer works on an app
in the Altinn Studio solution,-
-they are working on a clone
of the Central App Repository.
And when they're done
with their changes,-
-they can push their changes
to the App Repository.
This makes it easy
for multiple developers-
-to work on the same app
at the same time.
And all of the files are version
controlled, just like normal source code.
We have set up load balancer to route-
-between the Repository Application
and the Designer Application,-
-based on the URL that comes in.
Building applications through
a graphical user interface,-
-drag and drop, is cool.
Unfortunately, not all of
the functionality of the apps-
-is supported to be configured-
-through a graphical user interface
in Altinn Studio.
In addition, some developers might
actually like to use their own tools.
Especially when it comes to
writing code.
So we support local development.
Where app developers can use their
favorite tools to work on the apps.
So once an app is created,-
-it can be cloned to your local
computer where you can work on it.
Once you're done, you can push it
back up to the App Repository-
-for deploy.
One very important aspect
of developing an app is testing.
Apps need to be tested.
And the apps need the Altinn
Platform Solution to actually run.
One possibility is to deploy the app
to a test environment-
-where the Altinn Platform Solution
is running.
However, if you're just testing
while you are developing-
-and testing incremental changes,
this can be very time consuming.
So in order to support
local testing,-
-we have created a platform mock.
This can be downloaded and run
in parallel with the apps-
-in order to test the apps locally,
on the fly, while developing.
This platform mock is also used a lot
by the development team-
-when we're developing
new features for the apps.
Let's look at Deploy.
Apps are deployed
from the Altinn Studio solution-
-to a Kubernetes cluster
in the Altinn Apps Solution.
As Rune mentioned,
each app owner or government agency,-
-has their own Kubernetes cluster
to which they deploy their apps.
This is true for both
test environments and production.
This means that
the apps of one agency-
-do not affect the apps
of another agency.
And this is what allows us
to provide self-service deploys-
-all the way to production.
Deploy is a two-step process.
First we need to
actually build the application.
And this builds
a Docker image for the app,-
-and then pushes it to
an Azure Container Registry.
This is done via
an Azure DevOps pipeline-
-which you can see
an example of here.
Once the build is done,-
-we can deploy the app
to the environment that we choose.
And this fetches that Docker image-
-and deploys it to
the specified environment.
Again done using
an Azure DevOps pipeline.
Now Rune is going to show you-
-a little bit about
the Altinn Platform.
The Altinn Platform
is the part of our new platform-
-that contains all the functionality
needed by the apps.
We have grouped the functionality-
-into different containers
or micro services.
And those are available through APIs.
The first component is
the Authentification Component.
That's responsible for authenticating
the user and system-
-wanted to accessing an app.
The component works as
an identity provider for the apps.
This again is integrated with
other external identity providers-
-like the national ID port in Norway.
The Authorization Component
is authorizing access-
-for every app, the APIs and so on.
This is a XACML 3.0
Policy Decision Point-
-that reads the policy file defined-
-as part of the Application
Repository, just mentioned by Nina.
Every app will call
the authorization point-
-and get a response saying if
the user or system can access it.
We believe that this component can
be used in other types of scenarios.
It's available in our source code-
-and could be used
everywhere you can use a PDP.
Then you have the Profile Component,-
-where it gets the user information
for the users.
You have the Register Component-
-where you find information
about all the citizens-
-and businesses of Norway.
Often used in apps.
We have the Receipt Component-
-that provides a receipt for earlier
communication with the government.
All those apps I mentioned
are based on ASP.NET Core.
But the PDF component
is in fact a Java application.
We were not able
to find a good enough-
-open source PDF tool for .NET.
So if anybody wants to build it,
we'll truly appreciate it.
And then we have
the Receipt Component.
No, I'm sorry, the Storage Component.
Where you'll find the storage
functionality for the apps.
This is where the user
will end up storing their data.
This is also where the agency will
retrieve their data through the APIs.
So when a user submits data
in our app,-
-the app will call
this storage component,-
-and they will be stored down to
a separate storage account in Azure.
So those are the components we have.
The next step is what kind of
cloud architecture are we building?
Stephanie is going to give you
details about that.
Thanks.
We're going to talk a bit about
our public cloud components-
-and our architecure in Azure.
We're going to exemplify this
by looking at-
-how we deploy our microservices.
Microsoft established their first
Norwegian data centers this winter.
One placed East
and one placed West in the country.
This makes them
the only large cloud provider-
-with data centers in Norway.
Given that they have
two data centers,-
-we're able to have redundancy
within Norwegian borders.
This is great as we then
can take on application owners-
-that have a requirement that
their data is stored within Norway.
Another great thing about using
the Norwegian data centers,-
-is that we get a lower latency
in the communications-
-between our own premise
and cloud solutions.
Nina and Rune have told you about
our different microservices.
We have the different
platform components.
We also have the apps of our users
and Altinn Studio.
What I want to take you through,-
-is how do we get from
a bunch of code on GitHub or Gitea-
-to running services online.
The exciting thing is that
the concepts I'm going to show you,-
-are the same we use whether
we're deploying our microservices-
-or the microservices of our users,
the app developers.
The first step of course
is source control.
We use GitHub for all the code
that we're developing,-
-and Gitea for all the code
related to the applications.
At this stage, we also like
to run analysis on our code.
So we use LGTM, Looks Good To Me,
for security analysis,-
-and SonarCloud to ensure that
we have a maintainable code base.
That's just a few of the tools
that we're using.
So once we have
a new feature for the platform,-
-or an application owner decides
it's time to build their app,-
-a build pipeline is triggered
in Azure DevOps.
So this build pipeline is
made out of ready template tasks-
-in Azure DevOps,
making them really easy to configure.
It's a two-step pipeline
-where the first step
is building a Docker image-
-and the second step is pushing
that image to Container Registry.
Container Registry
is hosted in Azure,-
-and this is where we store
all of our images-
-until we're ready to deploy
the microservice.
There are two important things
I'd like to point out-
-about the Container Registry.
The first point being
that we are a public platform,-
-and our users must be able to trust
that their data is safe.
Going back to
the Isolation Principle.
This is why we have a container
registry for each of our application owners-
-where only their Docker images
are stored.
Secondly, a single Docker image might
be deployed to multiple environments.
So both testing and production.
This is why we treat
our Container Registry-
-and all the Docker images
as production resources.
Meaning that we set restrictions on-
-what and who is able
to access the resource,-
-as well as which availability
we're expecting,-
-and also which region
we're hosting the resource in.
Next step, once we have the Docker
image in Container Registry-
-and we're ready
to deploy the microservice,-
-is that we trigger
a release pipeline.
This is also hosted in Azure DevOps.
And this pipeline would use Helm-
-to install the microservice
on the cluster.
But I do have a confession to make-
-before we take a closer look
at the release pipeline.
Because we are
an open source project,-
-and we really like mentioning it
because we really like that fact,-
-but truth be told,
we do have an additional repository-
-which is protected.
This is where we store
sensitive data,-
-such as helm charts
and instrumentation keys-
-for some of our resources in Azure.
So this helm chart
and the other secrets-
-are packed as an artifact-
-and included into
the release pipeline that way.
What we see here, is an overview-
-of the release pipeline for
one of our platform components.
We can see that two artifacts
are included in the pipeline.
The first artifact is to identify
which Docker image we want to deploy.
The second artifact
would be the helm charts-
-from that repository
I was just mentioning.
Once we have the artifacts, we're
ready to deploy this microservice-
-to one of our environments.
What we can see here, are
all of our environments listed up.
In the first stage,
you'll find our acceptance testing-
-and load testing environments.
In the second stage,-
-we have the testing environment
for our application owners.
And then finally we have production.
So for these various stages,
we have different triggers.
With regards to
a platform component,-
-a new release would go to
the acceptance testing environment-
-whenever a new Docker container
is available.
Or a Docker image is available.
For our application owner testing
environments and also production-
-we have weekly releases.
We also have some manual checkpoints
prior to each release-
-to ensure that
we have people at work-
-in case something was to go wrong.
But the most important thing
about this release pipeline,-
-is the tasks that it completes.
The most important task
is that the pipeline-
-would run a helm upgrade
or helm install task-
-depending on if the microservice
has been deployed previously or not.
The result of this task,
is that a new pod will spin up-
-in the Azure Kubernetes
Services cluster.
Which brings us to the final step.
So a new pod spins up
in the Kubernetes cluster,-
-and the reference to docker image
is pulled onto the pod,-
-and the microservice starts up.
And it's always ensured that
the microservice is fully up and running-
-before we terminate any pre-existing
versions of that microservice.
This results in a deploy
without any downtime.
So this is our overall process-
-for getting from code on GitHub
to running services online.
And again,
it's the exact same process-
-whether we're deploying
our microservices-
-so a platform component
or the applications of our users.
But let's take a look
at how this looks in Azure-
-once all the microservices
are deployed.
So what we can see here,-
-is an overview of how we've
set up our infrastructure in Azure-
-for our different solutions.
Starting with Altinn Studio,-
-we can see that this runs in
a separate Kubernetes cluster.
We can see the two services, Altinn
Designer and Altinn Repositories.
Within Altinn Studio,
you'll also find a virtual network.
We have a key vault where
we store secrets and certificates-
-that are accessible
by the microservices.
And we have an Ingress route
to control the traffic-
-onto the correct node
running the pods.
And then we have a load balancer-
-to direct the traffic
to the right microservice again.
I think that's
the other way around, sorry.
So the load balancer handles
the incoming network traffic-
-so directing us to the correct node.
Then the Ingress route would direct
us to the correct microservice.
We can also see the connection here
to the build and release pipelines-
-that are triggered by users-
-when they're building
and deploying their applications-
-through Altinn Studio.
So the next component
is Altinn Apps.
And I think this might be the most
exciting part of our infrastructure.
So what we can see here,-
-are two examples
of application clusters.
And they've each got
four running applications.
So when an application owner
decides to join our solution,-
-they're given two
Azure Subscriptions.
One for their testing resources and
one for their production resources.
Within this subscription,
you'll find the Kubernetes cluster-
-where they host their microservices
or their apps.
You'll find the key vault
for sensitive data,-
-accessible by the microservices.
You'll find the virtual network,-
-the container registry
where we store the Docker images.
And you'll also find
the storage account.
In this storage account,
we'll store all the data-
-collected through
their applications.
And again we have the Ingress route-
-to control the incoming network
traffic and the load balancer.
And common for these apps,-
-is that many of them
would require the shared platform.
So the communication to get
from the apps to the platform-
-has to pass through
an application gateway-
-and then API management
before reaching our microservices.
So what we can see listed here,-
-are our different services
and the platform.
Each platform component
runs on their own Docker container.
We do actually have
quite a bit of communication-
-within these microservices as well.
Especially to
the authorization component-
-to authorize the different actions.
So this communication
is enabled through Linkerd.
We have an encrypted
pod to pod communication.
So this saves us
from routing that traffic-
-through the Internet and then
back to the same Kubernetes cluster.
I'd like to draw your attention
to the bottom component,-
-Platform Storage.
We can see that this component
would connect to Cosmos DB,-
-or a storage account,
depending on who owns the data-
-it's handling in
a given transaction.
We also our connection
to the on-premise environment-
-which is Altinn 2.
So this is enabled
with an express route.
And this gives us
a high-speed communication-
-between our on-prem
and cloud solution.
So looking at this infrastructure
as a whole,-
-there's a varying level of
how consistent the components are.
For Altinn Apps, for instance,-
-we'll be having new service owners
or application owners-
-wanting to join our solution.
Or we'll have requests to upgrade
some of their components.
Of course we have the standard work-
-like upgrading
our Kubernetes Services cluster-
-or our version of
Application Gateway, for instance.
We've struggled a bit
with finding a good way-
-to maintain our infrastructure.
But recently
we started using Terraform.
Terraform is a great tool
as it allows us both-
-to provision and evolve
our infrastructure.
Even better,
it's all written in code.
That allows developers like us
to take a much larger part-
-in both setting up
and maintaining our infrastructure.
This is because
we are able to read the code-
-and modify it to suit our needs.
And so looking at this picture,-
-you can see that there are
quite a number of cloud components-
-involved in setting up
our infrastructure.
And of course, some parallels
can be drawn to technology-
-that we've used on-premise,
but not always.
And so when we tried to select
which cloud components to use-
-or how to configure
our virtual network, for instance.
We've had to base our decisions
on the points that you can see here.
And I would say that
the point right at the bottom here-
-might be the most important one.
So which components
do we think have the potential-
-to evolve along with our platform-
-and the capabilities we expect
to deliver or offer in the future?
And I think this
says something about-
-daring to imagine
what the future looks like-
-or dream about
what we wish the future might be,-
-even though
we don't have it right now.
In some cases, it also means
doing the necessary work-
-to make sure that
our needs and expectations-
-are made clear to those
that are further developing Azure.
Here we can see
the most central cloud components-
-that we're using at the moment.
Luckily, a lot of these components
are fully managed by Azure.
This limits the number of variables
for us to tweak,-
-as well as the time we need to spend
maintaining these resources.
And we would have never
had to capacity-
-to have this many new components
in our solution all at once-
-if we were supposed to
manage them all ourselves.
And my reason for emphasizing-
-that these are the components
that we're using at the moment,-
-is that we do have a quite
high rate of change, I would say.
So we started
developing this solution-
-before the Norwegian data centers
were established.
This means that we've had to adapt-
-to which features would
be offered in Norway and not.
Also taking into account the rapid
evolution of cloud technology.
We're always prepared
to swap out a component-
-or to upgrade the existing ones
that we have.
Terraform, as I mentioned, is a great tool
for doing exactly that.
Another important thing for us lately
has been cost management.
With regards to
these cloud components.
If you're shy when selecting
a cost plan for these components,-
-the bills could quickly add up.
So we've had to sit down
and ask ourselves questions like:
Do we need the trace log
from our backup function?
And how long
are we actually willing to wait-
-to find log data
that's more than 30 days old?
And by asking these questions,
we've been able to...
Sorry, lost the thread there.
Let me just get back in.
So asking these questions, we've
been able to tweak our solution-
-in order to save cost
without compromising-
-the functionality of our solution.
So I'm going to talk about
some of the cloud components-
-that we're really happy with using.
The first one is
Azure Kubernetes Services.
As you can see
from our infrastructure,-
-we do have quite a number
of Kubernetes clusters.
And again, this is a great resource
because it's fully managed.
This means that
we have very few responsibilities-
-outside of deploying
our microservices and managing them.
In addition, Azure Kubernetes
Services supports autoscaling.
This means that our applications
are able to scale both up and down-
-depending on
the load that they're facing.
Once we've transferred
all of the application owners-
-from Altinn 2 to Altinn 3,-
-we're expecting to have
several hundred Kubernetes clusters.
So Microsoft's Azure team
might have a bit more to do,-
-but we should be able
to manage just fine.
We have Azure Cosmos DB.
This is a document database
that we use to store metadata-
-about the applications
and their instances.
Cosmos DB
is said to be highly available.
And it's documented
to have an availability of 99.999 %.
Pretty high.
And if that wasn't enough,-
-it also duplicates our data into
multiple locations automatically.
As this database is hosted in Azure,-
-you could say that we have
an unlimited amount of storage,-
-should we need it.
And at Microsoft Build,-
-autoscaling for Cosmos DB
was announced.
And we're really excited-
-to incorporate this feature
into our solution as well.
And finally, we've saved the best
for last, Application Insights.
So you know when you have a bug-
-and you're not quite sure
where the root cause is,-
-where to start debugging.
Application Insights would be
my starting point 9 out of 10 times.
So we use Application Insights
to monitor our microservices.
This goes for both the platform
components, Altinn Studio-
-and also all the apps
of our application owners.
App Insights will draw out an
application map as you can see here.
Where we can see
all of our microservices-
-and also the communication lines
between them.
Another feature that
Application Insights provides-
-is that we can drill down
to a specific timeframe-
-and see which requests
are used the most often,-
-and also
their average response times.
Another great feature
is drilling into a single request.
This way we can see how the request
flows through all of our services.
And these two features
that I just mentioned-
-have been heavily used
during our load testing.
We've been able
to identify bottlenecks,-
-and unnecessary
or duplicate requests as well.
So I'm going to hand you guys
over to Nina now.
She's going to share our experiences
working on this project.
We've been working on this project
now for a little over two years.
And we are definitely
some experiences richer,-
-and we would like to share some
of those experiences with you guys.
The first point
that I would like to make,-
-is that working on
an open source project-
-has been really great.
We have our backlog open on GitHub.
On the right side here
you can see a screen shot-
-from just a few days ago.
Having our backlog open on GitHub,-
-in addition of course
to our source code,-
-means that we have
gotten feedback and wishes-
-from the app developers
and government agencies-
-that have been
following this project-
-at a very early stage.
We've had app developers
submit issues-
-and they can follow
the progress of those issues-
-to see how they will be solved.
Now since we also only use
open source projects ourselves,-
-we can do the same.
So we can modify things
to suit our needs.
We also have great insight into
when new functionality-
-will become available in
the tools and frameworks that we use.
While having
an open backlog on GitHub-
-has been a really good thing,-
-"plain" GitHub as a tool-
-for managing the project
and managing the backlog,-
-has not worked that well for us.
Currently we are a quite small team,
and that makes it manageable.
But as you can see at the very top
of this screenshot from our backlog,-
-there are currently
almost 600 open issues,-
-and there have been a lot more.
So actually managing this
and prioritizing,-
-and seeing who is working on what,
has been quite challenging.
Especially previously
when we were a much larger team.
We've had to test several different
plug-ins to work with GitHub,-
-and we've ended up
with a plug-in called ZenHub,-
-which we feel
works quite well for us.
Finally a note on direction.
And we would like to say
that shifting direction mid project,-
-can actually be a good thing.
And now to elaborate
a little bit on that.
When we started this project,-
-we focused a lot around
the Altinn Studio solution-
-as a tool to build apps.
And we focused so much on the tool,-
-and possibly not enough
on the actual apps themselves.
We decided to switch our direction
to focus more on the actual apps.
This resulted in us having to-
-switch also from focusing
on users who do not know coding-
-towards users
who actually do know how to code.
I'm sure you've seen this reflected
in what we've been explaining today.
Probably you would need to know
at least a little bit of coding-
-to properly customize your app.
Hopefully going forward,
we can now continue-
-building on
the Altinn Studio solution-
-now that our apps are more mature.
I'll hand you over to Rune-
-who will tell you a little bit more
about our current status.
It's now 6,000 days since
Altinn 1 went into production.
It's 3,500 days since Altinn 2
went into production.
And it's over two years since we
started this minimum viable product.
So what is our status?
Are we done yet?
We went live on Monday, in fact.
It's a great success for us-
-that we are able to
launch this platform this Monday.
So this means that
the pilots are getting ready-
-to deploy their first applications
to the productions.
We are helping them out
with initial apps.
We have around 600 open issues,
as mentioned.
And we are still working from home,
but it works fine.
Forward, we're going to
focus on more stuff.
We have more than 1,000 digital
services on the old platform,-
-and we want to move that
to the new one.
So we will focus on building
more flexibility on the forms.
Being able to build more advanced
forms, components and so on.
We will expand the types of
process tasks we can support.
Like payment and signing we will add,
and many more.
This is
an event driven architecture,-
-and we need to define how
we're going to expose the events.
The goal for us
is to have an event feat-
-for every citizen of Norway,
every organization and every agency.
It's going to be an exciting task
to build that solution.
As mentioned many times,
we are open source.
Our documentation
is fully open source too.
And on GitHub you'll find a link to
the different documentation we have.
There you'll find full details
about the requirements,-
-both functional
and technical requirements.
The principles we have,-
-the different patterns we follow,
what kind of capabilities,-
-both the develop and runtime
capabilities of the platform.
And all the components
and code structure we are building.
Every design detail
you'll find there.
Take a look, you'll find details
about all the platform components.
And you will also find
the presentation we just had there-
-in a couple of hours.
I want to thank everyone for joining.
I want to thank NDC
for letting us come and present.
We are opening up
for answering questions.
I can see we have
a few questions on YouTube,-
-so we'll start here first.
The first question is:
Are the development teams
centered around those microservices?
Do we have an authorization team,
a PDF team, and etc.?
So are there different teams available?
Are they responsible
for the different services?
I guess the answer now: No, not yet.
We are currently not a big team,
so we are covering more components.
But there are special members of the team
that focus on different components.
So currently we have
one team sharing all components.
We're like 5-6 developers,
so it's not that big a team.
I don't even think
we have enough team members-
-to have a component each.
Another question here, let's see.
You mentioned that you
don't do multi-tenant architecture,-
-is this due to
a government requirement?
We of course investigate
what the government agencies need,-
-and some agencies would require-
-that they have an infrastructure
that is separated from others.
And we want to support
as many agencies as possible.
Based on history on the current
platform that is not separated,-
-we have seen instances of-
-poor code in one digital service
affecting others-
-because of high load.
So it's a natural experience,
and some requirements.
So another question
from Brian here is:
Since you're running multiple,
several hundred...
Soon to be several hundred,
we're not quite there yet.
So, since we're running
several Kubernetes clusters-
-and Application Insights, and Cosmos DB,
how are we hosting the costs?
-Do you want to answer that, Nina?
-Rune has the best answer for this.
Currently this is a governmental
platform, and it will be that,-
-and how the cost is shared,
is a deal that's between the agency-
-and the Norwegian
Digitalization Agency.
I think with the new architecture-
-it's more possible
to split the cost-
-if they want to,
to the different agencies.
On the current platform,
that's impossible,-
-because we are using
shared resources.
Saying that you are using 10 per cent
is not possible.
We've used examples
of application owners-
-with really large attachments.
Should we share those costs,-
-or should they be responsible for
paying for storing those attachments?
With our separate storage accounts-
-it's pretty easy to see how much
they're using and what it costs.
So another good question here.
Let's see.
Tom had the same questions as Brian.
Let's hope we've answered them.
We have Cybernetics100:
Despite all the good work
with the new Altinn Platform,-
-what are some top challenges
that still remain to be addressed-
-in or by the new platform?
We're taking too long to think here.
One thing that was
barely mentioned at the end,-
-was this idea of
being able to build the services-
-without having
a lot of technical background.
In the existing platform we do...
Yes, there are flaws,
but it is possible to build-
-a complete digital service
without having to know any code.
If you're going to build an app
in the Altinn 3 solution right now,-
-and you don't know
anything about coding,-
-it would have to be
a very, very simple app.
So extending that and making it
easier to actually build the apps,-
-that's probably something.
We have seen
during the development time-
-that when making it user-friendly,
it limits the flexibility.
I don't believe we want to go 100 %
user-friendly like we talked about.
I think it's easier.
We are learning kids to code, we
can learn the agencies to code too.
Pretty much, yeah.
Brian made a comment here
regarding the costs.
He's saying:
"ah, oil money. Say no more."
I guess that might be true.
We have another question here
from Steffen.
Could you say anything
about the advantages-
-that you gain from hosting
in the cloud versus on-premise?
-Do you want to take this one?
-Yes.
I was talking about
Application Insights.
So we're using that
only to react to instances,-
-or incidents at the moment.
But using this as a predictive tool
as well, I think would be great.
And also for our agencies
to get more feedback-
-on how their applications are used
and when they're used,-
-to be able to collect more data
about the citizens-
-or the companies
that they're interacting with.
I think another great thing
would be to run-
-larger analysis on the datasets
that they are collecting.
Because that's pretty easy
now that it's in the cloud.
Any other advantages?
I think the last thing you mentioned.
Having one common platform,
you have enormous advantages-
-in doing big data analysis
of the data going through.
For an agency, if they want to.
A final question.
Another one from Brian.
Azure DevOps, Azure API Management,
Cosmos DB.
Would we say that
we're heavily cloud locked,-
-if we were to decide to
go to a competing vendor-
-or go back to
an on-premise solution.
It's a good question.
One of the other principles
I didn't mention,-
-was to prevent that
we are locking ourselves in.
We have selected Cosmos DB,-
-but it's a document database, we
could replace it with something else.
API Management
probably will be more difficult.
We are not using so much
the features in API Management,-
-it's just a gateway for API,-
-so we could easily
replace it with another software.
It has been an important requirement-
-for the Norwegian
Digitalization Agency-
-that we're not locking in on Azure.
We are selecting Azure now. It could
be something else in the future.
It's important for us too.
We should get
some more data centers in Norway-
-before we could consider them.
I think that's about
what we have of time.
Thanks so much for watching us.
Reach out to us on
Twitter, LinkedIn, where ever.
And go see our code on GitHub.
-The link is right here.
-Make a pull request, please.